<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A detection and querimonie of the daily enormities and abuses co[m]mitted in physick concernyng the thre parts therof: that is, the physitions part, the part of the surgeons, and the arte of poticaries. Dedicated vnto the two most famous vniuersities Oxford and Cambridge. Nowe lately set foorth by Iohn Securis physition.</title>
            <author>Securis, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110907</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846361</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846361</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11323</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11844)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11323)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 551:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A detection and querimonie of the daily enormities and abuses co[m]mitted in physick concernyng the thre parts therof: that is, the physitions part, the part of the surgeons, and the arte of poticaries. Dedicated vnto the two most famous vniuersities Oxford and Cambridge. Nowe lately set foorth by Iohn Securis physition.</title>
                  <author>Securis, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Thomæ Marshi],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1566.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a A-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  England --  Standards --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Pharmacists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11323:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11323:1"/>
            <p>A Detection <hi>and Querimonie of the daily</hi> enormities and abuſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in phyſick, Concernyng the thre parts ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: that is, The Phyſitions part, The part of the Surgeons, and the arte of Poticaries. Dedicated vnto the Two moſt famous vniuerſities <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Nowe lately ſet foorth by <hi>Iohn Securis</hi> phyſition.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Non ferit haec medica praeſtantes arte Securis,</l>
               <l>Nec medici officio qui bene functus erit.</l>
               <l>Non ferit inſignes chirurgos, nec myropolas,</l>
               <l>Ars, quibus &amp; pietas, ſunt bene iuncta ſimul.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>1566.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11323:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11323:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CORDATISSIMIS, IM pendio<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> venerandis vtrius<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Acade<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miae, Oxoniinimirum &amp; Cantabrigiae Archigr<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mateis, Rectoribus, Decanis, Praeſidibus, Docta ribus &amp; Magiſtris: Iohannes Securts Medicus Academiae quondam Oxonienus alumnus, ſalutem in Chriſto Ieſu.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ampridem in animo me cum conſtitueram (viri longè clariſsimi) genio neſcio quo, niſi forte op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo (quatum certè mihi perſuadeo) inſtiga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te permotus, de abuſu ac cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptela artis noſtrae Hippocraticae, commentariolum quendam in lucem edere. Hoc tamen negotii eouſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuli ac ferè ſemper detrectaui, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, nec humanitas, nec literaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, nedum ipſa muſarum maieſtas,
<pb facs="tcp:11323:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
nec impoſtorum medicantium verſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, &amp; praeſtigiae, amplius me tacere, ea<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſilentio praeterire quae aduerſus peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſsimum hoc hominum genus adduci poſſunt, permitterent. Ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta ſiquidem vbi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> gentium ſed in hoc po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimum regno viget preſtigiatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, agyrtarum, inca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, veneficaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, veteratorum, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> adeo carnificu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me dicorum turba: qui quotidie huic ſeſe arti vi &amp; viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia intrudu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ac inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, adeo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſua, (prôh nefas) in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum necem ac perniciem experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta faciunt: vt mirandum mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis modis ſit, quin potius impenſé do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendum, ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tam id<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> impunè fieri Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginae ſubditorum ſtragem, tanta co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti piacula, ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>craſſos, ac foedos in ſancta ac chriſtiana republica (laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis
<pb facs="tcp:11323:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
velut hahenis effrenatae licentiae) errores perſiſtere, nedum reperiri. Verùm quum penſiculatiùs rem tota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> introſpicio, quum id quod res eſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum perpendo, ac arctiſsimè me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoluo: Non hoc vti<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vſquendeo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum eſse, nec recens natu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comperio. Quinimo à multis iam retro ſeculis, (ſi diuino Hippocrati credimus) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigit hanc celeber rima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medicinae ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, malè tractatam fuiſſe, ac foedis malè feriatorum hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> technis ac delyramentis, etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hippocratis aeuo, etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>num Galeni aliorum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> veterum medicorum fuiſſe aetate corruptam, conſpurcatam, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> polluta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nam vt Galeni verba ex primo lib. Therap<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> methodi iam ſubticea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Hippocratem lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gè Galeno veſtutiorem in medium
<pb facs="tcp:11323:4"/>
proferam in libello cui lex titulus eſtita loquentem. Medicina (inquit) omnium artium praeclariſsima eſt. Verùm propter ignorantiam eorum qui eam exercent, &amp; ob vulgi rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem quod tales iudicat &amp; habet: eò ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> res deuênit, vt omnium artium longe viliſsima cenſeatur. At vero hoc peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ob ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c potiſsimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſam mihi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitti videtur: Soli na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinae nulla poena in rebus publices ſta tuta eſt praeter<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ignominiae. Veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baecipſa non afficit ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> contingit eos qui ex compoſito perſonam ipſius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duerunt. Simillimi enim huiuſmodi medici ſunt perſonis quae in tragoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijs introducuntur. Quemadmodum enim illi figura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quidem &amp; habitum ac perſona eorum quos referunt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent:
<pb facs="tcp:11323:4"/>
illi ipſi autem verè non ſunt: Sic &amp; medici fama quidem &amp; nomme multi, re autem &amp; opere valde pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci. Idem Hippocrates in lib. de decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ornatu, ſic ait: Raptores medici ſunt qui fora frequentant, ruditate ac inſcitia ſua imponentes, &amp; in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis ciuitatum verſantes. Cognoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit autem quis ex veſtitu &amp; alijs li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neamentis. Quamuis enim fuerint ſplendidè ornati, multó magis fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi ſunt, &amp; à conſpicientibus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio habendi. Haec ille. His ita<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> iam perſpicuè ſatis ſuper<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> conſtat, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud veteres etiam primaeuae aetatis viros, fuiſſe in arte medica errones multos ac impoſtores. Vtcun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſit, hoc conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter adſeuerare non dubito, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tot olim medicaſtros, non tot vt ita
<pb facs="tcp:11323:5"/>
nominem Theriacarios, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tam mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos fucatos, perſonatos, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> phalera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, id<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vtrius<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſexus medicos fuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c noſtra aetate oppidatim, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo vicatim ſunt, &amp; videntur. Iſtuc proculdubio admirari nun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> deſino, quod leges cùm diuinae tùm Ceſareae in omnes ſi offenderint caeterarum artium homines animaduertant, in ſolos autem medicinae ſpurios gnatos, imo gnathones, &amp; ſycophantas non animaduertunt.</p>
            <p>Faxit precor Deus Opt. Max, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando, vtigrauiſsimo ac ſapientiſsi mo auguſtiſsimi Senatuſconſulti de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto: ſacroſancto Epiſcoporum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trocinio ac conſilio, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> veſtro pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (conſultiſsimi Academiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceres) pio vnanimi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuffragio, ſemel
<pb facs="tcp:11323:5"/>
velut poſtliminio reuocetur ſincera, vera &amp; germana rerum medicina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium adminiſtratio, verus vſus, &amp; ſic demu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vera cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolida doctrina me thodus. In rebus quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multis, praeci pue<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> quae ad religione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpecta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, refor matio ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pride<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facta eſt. Cur no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde in medicame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarijs facta ſit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sed ita res habentur humanae, vt quum nihil mali (hoc eſt nullus morbus) nos vrgeat, de malo profligando tan quám nimium ſecuri non cogitamus. Pleri<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ferè omnes dum ſani degimus ſanitatem non moramur nec magni pendimus. At vbi primum ſanitas euanuerit, tum demum velut Phry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſerò ſapere inchoamus, ac quid tum ſanitas, &amp; quam precioſus in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vita theſaurus fuerit, cum noſtro
<pb facs="tcp:11323:6"/>
ſaepe periculo igaui ac ſocordes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipimus. Caeterum, vt nunc tandem colophonem his dictis imponam, hoc opuſculum quod iam vernacula lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua perſtrinxi, vobis (clariſsimi iux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tà ac reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſs. Doctores ac Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri) tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrenuiſsimis ac optimis in hac cauſa futuris patronis, offerre nominatim, nuncupare<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> conſtitui. Munuſculum ſanè fateor indignum tantis viris, nihiloſecius tamen, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do pio beneuolo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> profectum ſit ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, benigno itide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animo, obnixè vos precor, ſuſcipere ne grauemini. Obſecro nunc tandem Deum patrem Seruatoris noſtri Ieſu Chriſti<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vt ſemper in virtute verbi ſui vos re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, protegat ac tueatur, veſtra om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia dirigat opera, omnes actus, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,
<pb facs="tcp:11323:6"/>
negotia, literas ac ſtudia: veſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtram<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> deni<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Academiam promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat magis magiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> in omne decus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> virtutem &amp; dignitatem prouebat: ad honorem, laudem &amp; gloriam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſancti nominis ſui in ſempiter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</p>
            <closer>Amen.
Idem vobis ſuprà memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus, &amp; nunc &amp; olim de uotiſsimus, Iohannes Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curis Medicus.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:11323:7"/>
            <head>This booke ſhalbe diuided in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to <hi>three principall partes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>¶ The fyrſt parte ſhall intreate of the manyfolde erroures and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of falſe and vnlearned phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
            <p>¶ The ſeconde intreateth of the ignorance, preſumption, and <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> of vniuſt Apothecaries.</p>
            <p>¶ The thirde part ſhall diſcuſſe of the raſhenes and lewde temeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a great many Surgeons.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11323:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11323:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11323:8"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>¶ The firſt part intreateth of dyuers and ſundrie errours and abuſes of the vnlearned and wycked ſorte of Phyſitions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT</hi> excellente man &amp; great clerk <hi>Ariſtoteles,</hi> who for his incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable doctrine is of all learned men named the prince of philoſophers hath this ſaying in the .vii. boke of his Ethikes: <hi>Non oportet tantum verum dicere, ſed etiam cauſam falſi aſsignare,</hi> that is: A man may not onely tell the truth, but he muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhewe and declare the cauſe of falſhod and errour. As who ſhold ſay: The truthe can neuer ſo well appere, as when it is compared to his contrary, which is errour, lye, and falſhode. <hi>Quia oppoſita ſemper
<pb facs="tcp:11323:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
iuxta ſe poſita, magis eluceſcunt:</hi> Contrary thinges ſet one againſt an other, are always a great deale better knowen.</p>
               <p>The philoſophers of ancient time as it appereth playnly in Ariſtotle and Galen, ye and in the holy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the churche. In many of their works, had in a maner more adoo to confute the falſe errours, ſophiſtrie &amp; cauillations that were then vſed &amp; imagined as true doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had to write the very truth it ſelfe. The great mercy of God had neuer be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo wel knowen if the fal &amp; tranſgreſſion of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had not ben. And as S. Paul ſaith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. v. chap. to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romans: <hi>Vbiexu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berauit peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ibi magis exubera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit gratia,</hi> Where ſyn hath exceded there grace hath the more exceded. And Chriſt in S. Luke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vii. cha. ſaid of Mary Magdaleu: Many
<pb facs="tcp:11323:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſyns ar forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her, becauſe ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued much. Nowe therfore, before I ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abuſes &amp; enormities of phiſike, I wil ſhew and declare firſt, what is the part office and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition of a good Phiſition. Thus doyng I wyl firſt alledge <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratis Iusiurandum,</hi> that is, the oth that Hipocrates wold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhuld take before he practiſe any phiſike. I wil not recite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole chapter, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefeſt parte firſt in latin, then in engliſh. <hi>Caeteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod ad aegros attinet ſanandos, dieta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro facultate, &amp; iuditio meo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modam, omne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> detrimentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et iniuria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ab eis prohibebo. Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro vllius preces apud me adeo vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae fuerint, vt cuipia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinaturus, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad hanc re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dabo. Similiter aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> muſieri talum vulnae ſubdititiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad corrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendum
<pb facs="tcp:11323:10"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceptum vel foetu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dabo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Porro praeterea, ſancte vitam &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſeruabo. Nec vero cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo laborantes ſecabo, ſed viris chi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rurgiae operarijs, eius rei faciendaelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dabo. In quaſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domos ingrediar, ob vtilitatem aegrotantiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intrabo, ab omni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iniuria volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taria inferenda, &amp; corruptione cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alia, tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praeſertim operum venereoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebo, ſiue muliebria, ſiue virilia, libe rorumue hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aut ſeruorum cor pora mihi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tigerint cura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da. Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vero inter curandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> videro aut audiuero, imo etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad medicandum non adhibitus in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni hominum vita cognouero, ea ſiquidem efferre non contulerit, tacebo, &amp; tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar cana apud me continebo.</hi> The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe is this: And as concernyng the curyng of the ſycke, I will or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyn and deuiſe for them as good
<pb facs="tcp:11323:10"/>
a diete as ſhall lye in my power &amp; iudgement. And I will take hede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei fal in no domage nor hurte. Nor yet any mans praiers ſhall ſo much preuail with me, that I geue poyſon to any man, neither will I counſaile any man ſo to do. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I will geue no maner of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine to any woman with chylde to deſtroy her childe. Moreouer I will vſe my life and ſcience godly. I will not cut thoſe that haue the ſtone, but I will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit that thyng onely to the Surgions. In what houſe ſo euer I ſhall come in, my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng ſhalbe for the pacients co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie and profite. And I wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine willingly from doyng any hurt or wronge, &amp; from falſhode, &amp; chiefly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venereous actes, what kynd of bodies ſoeuer it ſhal cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce me to haue in cure: whether it be
<pb facs="tcp:11323:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of fre or bond ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. And whatſoeuer I ſhal ſee or heare among my cures (yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I be not ſought nor called to any) whatſoeuer I ſhall know amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people, if it be not lauful to be vttered, I ſhal kepe cloſe, and kepe it as a ſecrete vnto my ſelfe: Again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſame Hippocrates ſaith in the boké or chapter called <hi>Lex.</hi> (To eſchue tediouſnes I wil leue the latin) who ſoeuer ſaith, he wyl truly get him the knowlege of phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſike, he muſt ſatiſfie his mynd, and as it were be accompanied with theſe guides, with nature, ſcience, a place mete &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient for ſtudy &amp; lerning, an inſtitution fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod, a labor &amp; peinful dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with a long tune. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his boke <hi>de me dico,</hi> he ſaieth: The phiſition muſt be of a good coloure, and comely countenaunce, and of a good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb facs="tcp:11323:11"/>
of the body: he muſte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be had in eſtimation among the common people, by comely appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, and by ſwete ſauours (ſo that he be not ſuſpected of to much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe) for by ſuche meanes the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientes are wont to be delited.</p>
               <p>In lyke maner the Phyſition muſte ſee and ſtudye, that he bee of a modeſt and ſobre mynde, and not onely as concernynge modeſt talke, but alſo in other things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his behauiour, he muſt be wel diſpoſed: for there is nothyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> getteth a man better eſtimation and authoritie then to bee endued with an honeſt lyfe and good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Hys countenaunce muſt be lyke one that is geuen to ſtudye and ſadde, and yet not ouer much, for ſo he ſhould be taken to be ſtub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>born &amp; ſcornful, &amp; like one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:11323:12"/>
other mens company: but on the contrary, he that hath always a laughing contenance, &amp; is geuen to too much ieſture and mirthe: is taken for a lewde perſon. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore this muſt nedes be eſchewed. Alſo he muſt be iuſt and beare him ſelfe vpright in all his buſynes and affayres. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In his booke <hi>De decenti ornatu</hi> he ſaith: a Phiſicion beinge a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher is equall in a maner vnto god. Item it is decent that the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion be gentyll and curteis, for rudeneſſe and churliſhnes are gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly miſliked, as wel of the whole as of the ſicke. He muſt often viſit his pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and be diligent. He may not declare all thinges to his pacient, but ſome things he muſt kepe cloſe from him, and muſt conforte him with a liuely &amp; mery countenance.
<pb facs="tcp:11323:12"/>
And ſometimes to withdraw him from his fonde deſiers, he muſte rebuke him, in reſiſting with ſharp words: and ſomtimes againe he muſt intreate &amp; conforte him, with a dexteritie and gentle perſwaſion. And yet notwithſtanding he may not alwaies tell him of his preſent ſtate, nor what ſhall becom of him.</p>
               <p>Thus much I haue brought out of <hi>Hipocrates</hi> to teſtifye &amp; declare the office and condition of a Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Now ſom thing will I bring out of <hi>Galen,</hi> who in his boke inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>quod optimus medicus idem e<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> et Philoſophus,</hi> declareth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the very title of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke it ſelf, what learning a Phiſicion ought to haue. He ſaith alſo in his boke <hi>de Antidotis,</hi> That a Phiſicion if it be poſſible oughte to haue the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of al herbes, if not, at the leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:11323:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he ought to knowe thoſe whiche be commonly vſed. Agayne in the commentaries vpon the fyrſt boke of <hi>Hippocrates de morbis vulgari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> The Phiſicion ſaith he ought in any wiſe to haue a reſpect to pro fit and helpe his pacientes, and if he can not, then at the leaſte wiſe that he hurt them not.</p>
               <p>Item vpon the vi. boke <hi>de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis vulgaribus</hi> he ſaith: Albeit that the phiſicion be gentle and curteis, ſober &amp; alſo mery, yet neuertheles he ought not to miniſhe his graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for vnleſſe the paciente haue in reuerence &amp; eſtimation his phiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a god, he ſhall neuer folow and obey his counſell, it wil be therfore very decent that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phiſicion do not ſo abaſe hym ſelfe &amp; flatter, that he bringe him ſelfe in a contempte: Nor agayne, as it were an other a
<pb facs="tcp:11323:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Eallianactes, ſhewe him ſelfe hog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh and rude. And that ſhal he ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely bring to paſſe, if in his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and talke and al his honeſt behauior, he retayne the grauitie of a phiſicion, and ſo do perſwade his pacient to followe and kepe thoſe things that he appoynteth and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayneth for him.</p>
               <p>But now leſt I ſhould be to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſe in alledging many authors: I will come to thoſe of our tyme, and namely I wil bring that man of high learning &amp; famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie maſter doctor <hi>Siluius,</hi> who ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>times was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publike reader of phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſicke in the vniuerſitie of Paris, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing daily at his Lecture litle lack of a M. auditors (or as they call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſcholars) of the which I being one, may plainly teſtify it to be tru The ſame <hi>Siluius</hi> ſaith in his boke
<pb facs="tcp:11323:14"/>
                  <hi>De ordine legendi libros Galeni e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hippocratis,</hi> that a good Phiſicion muſt haue al theſe properties.</p>
               <p>Fyrſt, he muſt be naturally bent and geuen to onely trueth, all the dayes of his life, he muſt be circum ſpect, diſcrete, and of a good preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant witte and memorie.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he muſt haue a ſounde and, healthye bodie, &amp; muſt be able to abide great payne in ſtudying.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he muſt be endued with great richeſſe, or at leaſte he muſte haue ſufficient to liue by.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, he muſt haue and get his learning of the beſt learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his time, who diligentlye, euen from his childhode muſt inſtructe him with theſe ſciences: grammer, Logick, muſicke, Aſtronomie, and chiefely (as Plato counſayleth) A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetick and geometrie, and alſo
<pb facs="tcp:11323:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Philoſophie.</p>
               <p>Nowe to come to my chiefe In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent &amp; purpoſe, &amp; (as they are wont to ſay) to the principal: Theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aboue rehearſed, well wayed &amp; conſidered: what hope may there be conceaued? what foundation &amp; ſtay may be had? yea what ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; ſauegard is there in theſe ſort of fellowes: which now a days al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in al places ſo raſhly, ſo fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſo wickedly do abuſe the no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble art &amp; ſcience of Phiſicke. Where is their great and manifold know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of the tounges, of the liberall ſciences, of Philoſophie, of anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, of the ſimples, of the compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d medicines, and of the temperatures or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plerions? wher haue they ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died? of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue thei learned their ſcience? (if I may call it a ſcience) what authors haue they ſene or red. Many
<pb facs="tcp:11323:15"/>
ſtanded without logike and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall philoſophie. For Ariſtotle ſaith <hi>Vbi deſinit Phyſicus, ibi incipit me dicus,</hi> A man muſt firſt peruſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Philoſophie, before he entre into phiſycke.</p>
               <p>I doo not denye but to haue ſome bokes of phiſike in englyſhe ſpecially of the Simples, well and cunnyngly ſet foorthe for Surge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Apothecaries, yea and for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and wyſe men, that delyte to reade in ſuche thynges, and know not the Latine tongue, is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete nor hurtefull. Althoughe I woulde not wyſhe, nor it is not decente, that eyther Surgion or Apothecarie, or any other manne, beyng no phyſition ſhould practiſe or vſe any inward medicine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the learned and approued phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions counſayle. For as the two
<pb facs="tcp:11323:15"/>
Prouerbes ſayeth: <hi>Falcem ne mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in meſſem alienam, Etne ſutor vltra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crepidam,</hi> Let no man medle with an other mannes corne, but with his owne. Lette the ſhoema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker meddle with his ſhoes.</p>
               <p>But to the pourpoſe, doo you thynke to haue in youre Englyſhe Bookes, all the perfecte knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that is required in Phyſicke? Yea, haue you the tenthe parte onely? We coulde neuer haue it yet in Greke and Latine perfectly (not wythſtandynge we haue it no we better then euer we hadde afore) howe thenne ſhoulde you haue it: If Englyſhe Bookes could make men cunnyng Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then pouchemakers, thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers plonghme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; coblers mought be Phyſitions as well as the beſt,
<pb facs="tcp:11323:16"/>
yf they can reade.</p>
               <p>Then wer it a great foly for vs to beſtow ſo much labor and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy all our lyfe tyme in the ſcholes and vniuerſities, to breake oure braynes in readynge ſo many au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, to be at the lectures of ſo many learned menne, yea and the greateſt follye of all were, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede in any degree in the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities with our great coſte &amp; char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, when a ſyr John lacke latin a pedler, a weauer, and oftenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes a preſumptuous woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhall take vppon them (yea and are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted) to mynyſter Medicine to all menne, in euery place, and at all tymes. <hi>O tempora, O mores, O Deum immortalem,</hi> To what purpoſe haue the vniuerſities ben<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erected &amp; founded in tymes paſte? To what purpoſe haue they ſo
<pb facs="tcp:11323:16"/>
many goodly priuileges graunted vnto them of al princes ſucceſſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from all ages? what doth it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile for vs that be lerned to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede (as I ſaide) in any degree of maiſter, of bacheler, or doctor, and ſo to be allowed and haue autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to vſe our ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? when euery man, woman, and chyld that lyſt, may practiſe and vſe phiſike (<hi>id<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> impune</hi>) aſwell as we? and ſo, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes not only hinder and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud vs of our laufull ſtipende &amp; gaynes: but (which is worſt of all and to much to be lamented) ſhall put many in haſarde of their lyfe, yea &amp; be the deſtruction of many. Is this tolerable? will the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates alwayes wynke at this? ſhall there neuer be no reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſuche abuſes? God of his great mercy grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ones they
<pb facs="tcp:11323:17"/>
may be refourmed. For if they be not, verily it wyll greately diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage men of learnyng hereafter to apply them ſelues to the ſtudye of Phyſyke, whereby the healpe; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and ſauegard of many a ſick man, woman, and chylde ſhall be hyndred and ſecluded: yea and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall fall in danger, and be ſicke which otherwyſe mought be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from al ſicknes by the right miniſterie of phyſike. For phyſyke is appoynted not onely to expelle ſicknes, but alſo to preſerue the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in healthe.</p>
               <p>But nowe to the thirde parte I aunſwere: you ſay that you heale many tymes by the gyfte of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: I praye you telle me what you meane by nature. Perhappes you vnderſtande by Nature; a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclynation or dyſpoſition,
<pb facs="tcp:11323:17"/>
geuen by the influence of ſtarres and planettes, (as I doo not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye but that we may be the better moued and inclined to any arte by theyr influence) yet is it not a mere gyfte, but onely a diſpoſition, and as it were a dexteritie and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall towardneſſe to heale ſom kind of diſeaſe: whych thyng notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng is oftentymes done more by chaunce, then by any certayne Methode or Reaſon. For verilye haue you neuer ſo good a wytte, diſpoſition and inclination to any arte: yet if you applye not that arte and exerciſe your ſelf in it earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and continually, and ſpecially in this ſcience of phyſike (whiche can neuer be well vſed without greate ſtudy, &amp; the knowledge of diuers other ſciences, as I haue ſaide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) your doyngs ſhalbe but raſhe
<pb facs="tcp:11323:18"/>
vayne, and of ſmall effecte. For as the philoſopher ſaith: <hi>Scientiae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, non innaſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, ſed acquiru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur,</hi> The ſciences ar not infuſed in vs at our byrth, but are gotten after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: And ſcience is thus defined in Logicke: Science is an habite, (that is) a ready, prompt and bent diſpoſition to do any thynge, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and gotten by long ſtudy, exerciſe and vſe. Therfore the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination by the influence of the ſtarres can profite but little, vnleſſe you applye your ſelfe with greate diligence and ſtudy to that kynd of ſcience or art that you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to practiſe and folowe.</p>
               <p>But yf you vnderſtande (by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) God: I ſay plainly, that god doth not geue the gyfte of healing to any wicked people, but only by a ſpeciall priuiledge to thoſe onely
<pb facs="tcp:11323:18"/>
that be of a moſte pure, ſobre, and holy lyfe, as we reade of the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and ſome of the Prophetes. And as ſainct Paule ſaythe in the firſt epiſtle, the .xii. chap. to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. To ſome is geuen the gyfte of healyng by the holy ghoſt. So that to hele by this maner of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, is not commonly to vſe her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, rootes, or any other drouges bought at the poticaries ſhop, or to take any money or other rewarde for the healynge. For this kynde of healyng is the mere gift of god workynge in thoſe (to whome it pleaſeth God to geue it) withoute any laboure or ſtudye. We heare of none nowe a dayes that hathe thys gyfte of nature (I meane of God) ſauynge onely the kynges of Englande, and the Frenche kynges, whyche as the Excellente doctour
<pb facs="tcp:11323:19"/>
ſhould be better and more honeſtly truely and iuſtely vſed and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred then it is nowe in theſe dais.</p>
               <p>And becauſe that I would that euery man ſhould ſee and knowe, what articles they be that I dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, I haue thought it good to take a copie of them (which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I haue ſomwhat al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered) and rehearſe theym here in order.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Seuen Articles concerning the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration and vſe of Phiſike.</head>
                           <div n="1" type="article">
                              <head>The fyrſt.</head>
                              <p>It were very mete, expedient &amp; neceſſary that no phiſition ſhoulde practiſe phiſicke in any dioces, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les he were fyrſte allowed by ſome vniuerſitie: or at the leaſte hauing ſufficient learninge in the ſaide ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he were allowed and licenſed by the byſhop or his chaunceloure in that dioces wherin he dwelleth.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="2" type="article">
                              <pb facs="tcp:11323:19"/>
                              <head>The ſecond.</head>
                              <p>It were good and neceſſarye that no Surgion ſhoulde practyſe his ſurgery, vnles he coulde reade and write, and had knowledge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in the ſimples belonginge to his art. And that he preſume not to let bloud or vndertake any hard cure, without the phyſitions coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, if he may conueniently haue it.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="3" type="article">
                              <head>The thyrd</head>
                              <p>That no Poticarie ſhould mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his owne heade, or ordeyne any purgation or other compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Phiſicke for any man: or that he ſhoulde prepare and make any purgation or notable confection, withoute the Phiſitions aduyſe and counſell, vnles that the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition hadde fyrſt ſene and vewed the Ingredientes, wherof the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſitions are made, and ſpeciallye the purgations.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="4" type="article">
                              <pb facs="tcp:11323:20"/>
                              <head>The fourthe.</head>
                              <p>It is not decent nor profitable for the common weale, that any igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant lewde or ill ſuſpected perſon, be he man or woman, ſhoulde be ſuffered to make, ſell or miniſter medecines to any bodie, but that ſuche kind of perſons (beyng duely examined and conuyeted by the learned Phiſitions of the dioces) ſhould haue condigne puniſhment appoynted them by the Byſhop or his chauncelour.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="5" type="article">
                              <head>The fyfthe</head>
                              <p>That no Phiſition do take vpon him the name of anye degree of Schole, as bachelour, maiſter of Arte, or doctor: or cauſe and permit any writer or printer ſo to terme him, vnles he can approue it to be ſo in dede by any vniuerſitie.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="6" type="article">
                              <pb facs="tcp:11323:20"/>
                              <head>The ſyxte.</head>
                              <p>That no midwife ſhould diſdayne to come aſke counſell of the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as often as any woman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in laboure of childe, is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. It were good alſo that the midwiues wer firſt ſworne to the byſhoppe, before they take vppon them their office.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="7" type="article">
                              <head>The ſeuenth.</head>
                              <p>It were alſo good and expediente that (as the vſe of London is, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by an acte of Parliament) that the Phiſitions in euery other dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces one or two, or more, ſhold haue licence of the byſhop, to ſearche and vewe the poticaries ſhoppe once a yere at the leaſte, and ſee whether their ſtuffe and medecines be good and lawfull or not.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Theſe Articles aboue rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed I thought good here to allege, (although
<pb facs="tcp:11323:21"/>
                  <hi>gora,</hi> the roote of Gentian: for <hi>Hęmatites, A methyſtus:</hi> for <hi>Semper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuum minus,</hi> the herb called thriſt or greate Stonecrope, they haue taken litle Stonecrope in making their <hi>Populeum,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the purpoſe, where as the acte preſuppoſeth a ſpeculation or practiſe, they practiſe at a venture a thynge whiche they knowe not, whether it be colde or hotte, drye, or moyſte.</p>
               <p>Item, where as the Act geueth them licence to myniſter drynkes for the ſtone, ſtrangurie, &amp; agues: They knowe not the ſtone in the back, from the ſtone in the blader: neither whether the ſtone may be waſted and broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by drinkes and powders, or had out by inciſion. Moreouer thei know no differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene a colyke and a ſtone: for
<pb facs="tcp:11323:21"/>
they name them bothe one, where as they be two ſundry diſeaſes. They know not what <hi>Stranguria</hi> is, nor how many maner of ways it may be engendred in the bodye. They can ſcant diſcerne a tertian ague from a quotidian. As for the mixt and complicate agues, they know not what to make of them They call them newe diſeaſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they can geue them no other name.</p>
               <p>Nowe in good faithe, yf theſe ioly felowes had but that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge onely, which the ſaid act pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth theym to haue: it were not ſo great a danger, if they ſome tymes were permytted to geue ſome medicines for the foreſayde dyſeaſes. But I praye you, howe manye of theym haue that litle knowledge? which knowlege
<pb facs="tcp:11323:22"/>
is but lyttle in dede in compariſon of many other ſciences, whiche be not onely profitable, but alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to attayne the noble ſcience of phiſike. If the other actes which hath ben made for the reformation of Phyſike, be well ſcanned &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred togither one with an other, it ſhal plainly appere, that the afore named act, ſhal not make ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for theyr purpoſe, who by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and raſhneſſe do vſe to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe phiſike at theyr pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Verily I muche meruaile at one thynge that many which be of the higher ſort, reputing them ſelues to be of no ſmall grauitie &amp; wiſedom will ſometymes geue credite to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lewde perſons, counterfayting the phiſitions. In dede I ſuppoſe that they be partly deceiued by the vain perſuaſions &amp; faire flattering
<pb facs="tcp:11323:22"/>
ſpeche of ſuche fellowes. Their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication is ſo faire, ſwete, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till, pleſant and amiable: and their promiſe and waranting ſo earneſt and great, that they will go nye to deceaue the wiſeſt man that is, yf he haue not the more grace, and be very ware of them. And the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to allure the ſymple people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: They wil ſay to him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do take in hand: Syr, I will nonne of your money no we vntil you be whole: I will haue money only of you for the medicins, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I muſt occupy for your diſeſe. They wyll lyghtly warrant euery manne to heale hym, of what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe ſoeuer he hath: And for all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly but two or three ſortes of medicines, and yet moſte commonly they be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations or vomites.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11323:23"/>They purge ſo muche and ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that they purge many tymes as wel the ſowle out of the body, as the money out of the purſe.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, theſe fellowes will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo (to haue the more credite geuen vnto them) name them ſelues af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſom great lerned mans name. Somtunes they fain them ſelues to be of ſome ſtraunge countrey, and wyll counterfayte their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage (As I know one in Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury) and loke to be called by ſom name of dignitie or worſhyp: as Maiſter, gentylman, domine, doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and al to deceaue the people.</p>
               <p>O I would wyſhe, that euery man woulde take hede, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche God that euery man may be ware of ſuche falſe Phyſytions, whyche maye be lykened to wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues or foxes, clothed outwardlye
<pb facs="tcp:11323:23"/>
with lambes ſkyns, but inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are full of ſubtiltie and deceite. Many periſhe through the yere at their nands, wherby the good ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of phyſike is brought into an obloquie and reproche.</p>
               <p>Many learned doctours of oure time haue in their works inueyed greatly agaynſt theſe abuſes, and haue wiſhed ſom puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be eſtablyſhed by the Maieſtrates, vnto ſuch as wickedly and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all reaſon myſuſe and practiſe this ſcience.</p>
               <p>Here I coulde alſo ſomewhat touch ſome of the lerned ſort, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che although they bere themſelues neuer ſo ſtoute, and appere to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do all things wel: yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, they halt ſomtimes on bothe ſides: They ſe &amp; know many abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poticaries ſhops, and yet
<pb facs="tcp:11323:24"/>
they winke at the matter, and are loth to diſpleaſe the poticarie, who perchance is their frende. But the prouerbe ſaithe: <hi>Amicus Socrates, amicus Plato, Amica tamen magis veritas,</hi> The truthe ought to take place in all thynges, and aboue all thynges.</p>
               <p>There be alſo many phiſitions, that thynketh them ſelues ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly lerned, that they beleue that no man is able to match with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in lerning, they be ſo arrogant and ſcornful, that although the pacient hymſelf be content to haue the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayle of two or three other phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to conſult and conferre togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of hys diſeaſe: yet they wyll not wyllyngely graunte to it, but rather diſdayne to conferre with any other, the whyche perchance are ſommetymes a greatte deale
<pb facs="tcp:11323:24"/>
better learned then they are. They remember not what <hi>Hippocrates</hi> their maiſter ſaith, in his booke <hi>de preceptionibus,</hi> who being in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin tranſlated ſaith thus: <hi>Nec vero indecore ſe illegeret medicus, quiin rei praeſentis auguſtia circa aegrum aliquem, et imperitia tenebras of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, alios quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> accerſere iuſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, quo ex co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni conſideratione, res circa aegrum inquirantur ac cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcantur, &amp; illi cooperatores fiant ad auxilli ferendi facultate.</hi> The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe is thus: That phiſition ſhall not do amiſſe, nor behaue himſelfe vncomly, which beyng as perplex in the buſines about his paciente, and doubtfull for want of perfecte knowledge: do cauſe other phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be called, that by common deliberation, and conferringe one with an other, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pacientes affaires
<pb facs="tcp:11323:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11323:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11323:26"/>
may be dewly examined and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that they may be as coadiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, helpers one to an other) to prouide for ſome remedy. Some there be alſo (leſte I wene that other men ſhould learne their cunning) that wil rather ſcrible the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> write a recept, and will make ſuch daſhes and ſtrange abbreuiations in theyr billes, that theyr writinge ſemeth rather to be arabicke, or like the writinges of the Cabaliſtes, then Latin. I feare me that they that write ſo, are aſhamed of their owne occupation, and feare leaſte that if they ſhoulde write playne, their errours and faultes ſhoulde be eſpied. He that is a playne man will deale<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> playnelye, will ſpeake playnely, and write playnely.</p>
               <p>Some ther be alſo that be ſo ſtiffe necked &amp; heady in theyr opinions,
<pb facs="tcp:11323:26"/>
that they will be of no man gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde in no wyſe, no and if you bringe them neuer ſo good a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, although you alledge them ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo many authorities.</p>
               <p>But I ſay, <hi>Plus vident duo ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vnus.</hi> All the wit of the worlde lyeth not in one mans heade. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to conferre together vppon a matter, it doeth oftentimes greate good, and no man (be he neuer ſo well learned) ought to refuſe it, as often as time, place, or any other oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſion ſhall ſerue.</p>
               <p>Item, ſome phiſitions ther be, that be ſo greedy and of ſo an vnſacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſier, that they care and paſſe not in what daunger they caſte them ſelues in, what ſhame &amp; da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage they ſuſtain, ſo that thei may haue many cures, wher ſomtimes
<pb facs="tcp:11323:27"/>
one would ſuffice the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> well enough and be more perchaunce then they can well bring to paſſe. They be ſo couetous that they wold haue all, and do al them ſelfe, and they haue enuy many tymes at other honeſt men hauing cures, when they haue none. Thys doinge verelye they bringe them ſelues in greate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte, and dothe as it were abate and blemiſhe the honorable ſcience of phiſicke, which requireth rather to be ſought earneſtly with greate ſute, with humilitie, reuerence and prayinge, then to be offered, and as it were obiected vndiſcretely to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man, and in euery place, lyke a blinde harpers ſonge or a Ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars packe. The common prouerbe ſaith, that offered ſeruice ſtynketh. And I haue harde oftentymes ſaye, that phiſicke vnles it be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb facs="tcp:11323:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſought and well payde for, it will neuer proſper nor woorke well with the pacientes, I meane not by this but that the Phiſition muſte be alwayes liberall and mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifull to the poore, on whom his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing dependeth not but on the rich Nowe to conclude and finiſh this fyrſt part, I will leaue to intreate any more of phiſitions, (except as occaſion ſhall ſerue) and nowe in the next parte followinge I will ſpeake of poticaries, &amp; touche ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what their abuſe and negligence. Whoſoeuer wil read anye more of the tokens and qualities of foliſhe and blynd phiſitions: Let him rede a litle boke of mine, printed about a doſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yeres paſt, which is intituled: A gret Galley lately com into Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land òut of <hi>Terranoua,</hi> laden with phiſitions, poticaries &amp; ſurgio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. &amp;c. made in forme of a dialoge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11323:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Seconde parte intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi> of the ignoraunce and preſumption of certayne Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſpeciallye to thoſe that be truly and exactly lerned in phiſick, that ther hath bene, is now, yea and ſhall be (if ſome good order be not taken) great abuſes among poticaries, in handling, keping, choſing and dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their drouges and medecines. In ſo much, that it is ſuſpected of moſt part of men (and I pray god it be not ſo in dede) that amonge all other mechanicke artes or occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations, the greateſt &amp; moſt crafty
<pb facs="tcp:11323:28"/>
deceate that is, is or may be in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries. Howbeit, I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, but that within theſe fewe yeres, ſome poticaries, by the helpe and counſell of good Phiſitions, haue gotten and prouided for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtuffe &amp; ſimples to make their compoſitions, then they wer wont to haue afore.</p>
               <p>And I beleue verely, that if euery poticarie would endeuour himſelf to bye no ſtuffe, but that ſhould be pure and good: there woulde be a great meany, that would geue bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter credite to phiſitions and Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, and haue a better hope in them, then they haue now a daies, and all becauſe they miſtruſt and ſuſpecte ſo muche the Poticaries ſtuffe and confections. In dede, as couetouſnes is the roote of all euyll, ſo many poticaries there be,
<pb facs="tcp:11323:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that more for lucre ſake and gredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of worldly goodes, do prepare their medicines, then for any care that they haue, to deale truly with the poore pacientes and ſely ſoules that be in payne. The phiſition ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes ſhall ordeyne his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and appoynt certayne mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines for his pacient: which mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines he knoweth certainly ſhal do him good, beynge taken and vſed accordinge to his counſell, yet the ſame medecines beyng taken and bought at the poticaries, and made many tymes of noughty ſtuffe, or not well prepared, ſhal not only do litle or no good at all, but ſhall alſo ſomtimes put the ſicke body in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarde of his lyfe, whereby ſhall no ſmall trouble and ſhame redounde vnto the phiſition, and yet was he not the occaſion thereof, nor in any
<pb facs="tcp:11323:29"/>
fault at all. Some perchance wil alledge agaynſt the phyſition, that he maye bee in the faulte, for as muche as he ought to haue ſeene the ſtuffe fyrſte, whereof the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are made, and ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to haue ben at the makyng and preparyng of the medicines whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he ordeyneth.</p>
               <p>In dede it ought to be ſo, if all thynges went well, and ſpecially if the poticary be ſuſpected to haue ſomwhat a large co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, or that he be of a ſlender learnynge and negligente, and paſſeth not what he doothe, ſo that he may receyue money. But you muſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that the phyſition can not alwais be preſent at the makyng or dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerynge of ſuche medicines as he hath appointed. For ſomtymes he hath mo pacientes to loke to then
<pb facs="tcp:11323:30"/>
one, &amp; perchance he may be twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or forty myles from the potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, when he ſendeth his bylle to hym, and therefore can not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Many other occaſions there bee, that letteth the preſence of the phiſition at the makynge and dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryng of medicines.</p>
               <p>But yf the apothecarie be an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, of a good conſcience and learned: Or that he hathe ſuche a one vnder hym to ſerue the ſhoppe that is of lyke qualities: It is not then ſo greatly neceſſary for the phi ſytion to be preſent, ſo often as he ordeyneth his counſayle for anye paciente. For euen as a good tree wyll alwayes brynge foorth good fruite: So wyll a good poticarye make and delyuer nothynge at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye tyme, but that that is lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and good. But this queſtion
<pb facs="tcp:11323:30"/>
(yf a man moughte be ſo bolde) I woulde fayne aſke, howe manye good apoticaries bee there in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland? howe many doo theyr due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as they oughte to doo? Howe many are learned: howe many are faithfull? and howe many are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng and deſyrous that the phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhoulde ſee theyr drouges, and ſee the makynge of their compoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? Many ther be, that diſdayn that the Phyſitions ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente at the makyng of theyr me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicins, and who more then the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, couetous &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentious ſort of poticaries. The ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thynkes (folowyng their barbarous Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans) that their knowlege (whiche is mere ignorance) farre excellethe and ſurmounteth the knowledge of all Phyſitions. The couetous ar aferd, leſt yf the phyſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:11323:31"/>
be preſent they ſhould find a great deale of theyr ſtuffe to be ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, corrupt and nought.</p>
               <p>There be alſo an other ſorte of Poticaties, which be ſo arrogant and ſcornfull (by reaſon that they de growen in greate richeſſe God knoweth how) that they diſdayn the Phyſition, and haue hym in no eſtimation, where as in the an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient tyme, the poticaries (as Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene and other wytneſſeth) were but as ſeruauntes and miniſters vnto the Phyſition. <hi>Galen</hi> in the commentaries vpon the .vi. boke of <hi>Hippocrates, de morbis vulgari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> ſaythe thus: The miniſters of the phiſition, are gatherers of her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, oyntemente makers, cookes, playſter makers, clyſter geuers, ſcarifiers, letters out of bloud. &amp;c. but yf we (meanyng of phyſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:11323:31"/>
after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue lerned theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, do alſo ſomtimes the like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we doo no otherwiſe then euen as a maiſter or gouerner of a ſhyppe, whyche hauynge knoweledge in rowyng, do rowe when he lyſte, and get vp to the top of the maſt, and dothe all other thynges belon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng to the mariners arte and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Thus muche Galene.</p>
               <p>I neede not to alledge here the xxxviii. chapter of Eccleſiaſticus, where euery manne is exhorted to honour the phyſition: how much more then ſhould the poticarie ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reuerence hym, whiche hath chiefly his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uyng by meanes of the phyſition. I ſpeake not this bycauſe I or any phyſition ſhould ſeke worldly honor, or vain glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For aboue all thynges: <hi>Soli Deo fit honor &amp; gloria.</hi> yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng,
<pb facs="tcp:11323:32"/>
accordynge to Saincte Pauls doctrine, we ought to geue honour, to whome honour belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth. I remembre that whenne I was yet in a maner but a boye in age, ſtudying beyonde the ſea, after a yeare or two that I had ſtudied in phyſicke: I woulde ſomtymes (for to haue the better knowledge in ſymples) reſorte to ſome potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhoppe or other. But I ſhould no rather come into the ſhop (ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of learned and honeſte men) but that immediately, The potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie woulde welco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me and receyue me with all curteſſye and humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ryſe from his ſeate to geue me roume, and ſo woulde enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn me with all gentylnes that he mought. This dyd they to me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then but a ſcholer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what would thei do think you to the maiſters &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11323:32"/>
doctours of phiſike? What maketh many poticaries now a days to ſet ſo litle by the phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: This is one chief cauſe: They play the phiſitions them ſelues, they geue and miniſter medicins of their own deuiſe (god wote a mad deuiſe) indifferentely vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yea and the more igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant they are, the more bolder they be. For who is ſo bold as blind bay ard? Many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil not ſticke to loke in waters, &amp; be not aſhamed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the phiſitions preſence, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyn this or that medicine for any kind of diſeaſe: If any phiſition do gently admonyſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their fault &amp; ſpecially of geuyng of medicines after their owne brayne: They wyl ſay, that they may as<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> well preſcribe medicines, as Phyſitions ſomty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes doo vſe to make them. They may playe (ſaye they) as well the
<pb facs="tcp:11323:33"/>
Phyſitions, as the phyſitions play the poticaries, as though a phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and a poticary were all one. In dede a phyſition may be a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticarie, and haue a poticaries ſhop within hymſelf in his owne hous or maye be a Surgeon, and heale wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des or ſores, or let bloud him ſelfe: <hi>Sed none diuerſo.</hi> A Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catie or Surgeon beyng onely of that arte may not be a phyſition, vnleſſe he abuſe and falſely exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe againſt all reaſon and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, (as many do nowe a days) the ſcience of phyſike.</p>
               <p>To proue that a phyſition may make or cauſe to bee made in hys owne houſe, any kynd of medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: it may partely appere by the authoritie of Galene afore alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and alſo by dyuers other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous authors of our tyme, and
<pb facs="tcp:11323:33"/>
ſpecially by <hi>Manardus</hi> and <hi>Siluius. Manardus</hi> in the prologe prefixed to the annotations vpon Meſue, hath theſe wordes: In times paſte ſaithe he, the phiſitions themſelues prepared the medicines at theyr own houſes, and ſo kept them rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made, the whiche as often as nede required, accordinge to their diſcretion and the neceſſitie of the ſicke, they vſed. But ſins theſe fiue hundred yeres or there about, this kind of buſines hath bene commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or rather deriued from the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions (not withoute as I beleue the danger of the pacientes) vnto certayne, which are called ſpicers, or Poticaries. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacobus Siluius</hi> in his boke <hi>de me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicamentorum ſimplicium delectu,</hi> in the beginninge, wheras he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the dewty of a Poticarie:
<pb facs="tcp:11323:34"/>
declareth, that as well <hi>Galen</hi> as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther phiſitions did oftentimes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the medecines them ſelues. It is lawfull then for the phiſition (if he lyſte) to prepare the medecines for his paciente him ſelfe: but not lawfull for the poticarie, to vſe or practiſe phiſicke for any man, of his owne heade.</p>
               <p>I wold wiſh that the poticarie, as he is deſirous of gayne, ſo he wold prouide for all things neceſſary for his ſhop, and chiefly and fyrſt of al, for the chiefe guide &amp; Inſtrument, that ſhold rule al the roſt, I meane the boke of <hi>Bernardus Deſſennius Cronenburgins, de compoſitione medicame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>torum:</hi> The perfecteſt in my opinion, &amp; moſt excellent booke I beleue, that euer was made for poticaries, Howbeit, becauſe that ſome phiſitions vſeth the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions
<pb facs="tcp:11323:34"/>
of other authors: I would wiſh alſo, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poticarie mought not be without the diſpenſatories of <hi>Valerius Cordus,</hi> of <hi>Euchſius,</hi> or <hi>Nicolaus Mirepſus,</hi> or the .ii. bokes of <hi>Siluius,</hi> contening the choſinge, kepinge, and making of medicines commonlye uſed: or <hi>Examen tam ſimplicium <abbr>q</abbr> compoſitorum, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonij Muſae:</hi> and not to followe ſtill their blinde <hi>Nicolaus Praepoſitus,</hi> which is full of errours. It were mete and conuenient alſo, that the Poticaries had diuers fearces to ſearce their powders in, for ſome powders would be ſea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ed verye fynely, as they that be diureticke powders, and moſt parte of Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaries: ſome more groſſye, as the moſt part of laxatiues, except aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke and colocinthis.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11323:35"/>
a pound of ſuger, to an ounce of powder. And to ſay my fancie and opinion: it were good that the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhould determine &amp; appointe in his byll, howe muche ſuger he wold haue to be put with the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der. For ſomtimes it layneth that he ordeineth a purgation in loſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis: ſomtimes he vſeth ſome bitter powder, or very hote powder, that requireth of ſuger more or leſſe: but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly bitter or very hot pouders require more ſuger: and pleaſant &amp; temperat pouders require leſſe: but many poticaries are very liberall, which ſpare for no ſuger, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they make loſengis, becauſe they haue more reſpecte to their profite, then to the pacientes healthe. Agayne they loue to make all thynges pleaſaunt and ſwete, ſo that ſwete money maye come in. And it is
<pb facs="tcp:11323:35"/>
mooſte commonlye ſeene, that the moſte parte of ſicke folke abhorre ſwete things. Wherfore, they ſhold know of the phiſition (vnles he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it him ſelfe in his bill) how much ſuger he will haue to the ma king of the medecines.</p>
               <p>Nowe at the laſte to conclude, becauſe that poticaries ſhall know partely what theyr dewtie is, I will here recite what <hi>Siluius</hi> ſaith in the place afore alleged, of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries duety. And thus I haue tranſlated his preface into engliſh.</p>
               <p>Althoughe that the Potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie be endewed with many thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, commonlye agreynge with the Phiſition: as with natural diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, a perfect knowledge of the medicines, a gret dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in al ſuch things as belong to his office, &amp; an honeſt behauiour: yet neuertheleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:11323:36"/>
many thinges are in a maner pecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liarely appropriated vnto him, the which ſomtimes were alſo proper and belonging vnto the phiſitions, at what time they them ſelues pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared the medicines, as it appereth that <hi>Galen</hi> ſhould haue done it, in manye places by his writinges. Nowe ſuche thinges as be proper to the poticaries are theſe: The cho ſinge of medecines gotten by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and longe experience, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the maner to kepe them, and to knowe the time when they are in their power and force, or when they are deſtitute from all vertue and corrupte. Alſo, howe and in what maner eche of them ought to be vſed, eyther by it ſelfe alone, or els to ſethe it, or to bruſe or breake it with other, or to prepare it after an other ſort and maner. It is alſo
<pb facs="tcp:11323:36"/>
conuenient and neceſſary for a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticarie to knowe his grammer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he may the better vnderſtand the compoſitions of the aunciente writers, and alſo the dayly writin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (which commonly they call re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes or billes) of the Phiſitions. In the whiche writinges, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes they haue write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thing more or leſſe then nede is, or more vnpleſaunt then the poticarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectureth in him ſelfe, to be mete &amp; conuenient for the pacient: he then may gently tel and warne the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of it.</p>
               <p>Moreouer we would that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticarie knewe perfectly the art and ſcience to chooſe the medicines, to prepare them, and to compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together. We would alſo haue him to be contented with a meane ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, to be mery and pleaſaunt in
<pb facs="tcp:11323:37"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication after an honeſt ſort, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the pacientes buſines, to be no couetous, no laſciuious, no dronkerd nor contentious perſon: all which thinges are euen in lyke maner to be obſerued of the phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as of the poticarie, as <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> teſtifieth in his boke called the office or duety of a phiſition.</p>
               <p>And if the poticarie be indewed with ſuch perfections of ſpirite, of the bodie &amp; alſo of fortune: he will neuer geue any medecine (ſpecially being of any gret operation) to any man, vnles he be of the counſell of ſome cunning phiſition, nay nether will he geue any thing, be it of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo litle effect, knowing not the vertue of it. For ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times certayn remedies, although they ſeme but weake, yet neuertheleſſe throughe quantitie, qualitie and ſpace of time
<pb facs="tcp:11323:37"/>
beyng vnholeſome, or the occaſion many times of great diſeaſes, and taketh away the righte and trewe way of curation: In ſo much that vnder ſuch remedies, the bodie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge in cure, will ſone afterwarde beare greater &amp; ſtronger remedies, but not conuenient to the purpoſe. Moreouer he ſhal not commit any crime or fault, either for loue or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure, or for hatred or feare: nor he may not be ſeduced by money or led by ignorance. Neither ſhal he geue at any time any poyſon, or thinges procuring abortion, any thing that is to olde or out of vſe, thinges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and ſophiſticate, or any <hi>quid pro quo.</hi> But he ſhall aſke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, (as often as nede ſhal require) of a well learned Phiſition, what ſimple or compounde medycyne is to be ſubſtytuted and taken,
<pb facs="tcp:11323:38"/>
for lacke one of the other. Nee ſhall not augment nor fortifie the quantitie of any ſtrong medicine, to the intent that by a greater eua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuation enſuyng, men ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him to haue better poticaries ſtuffe then any other.</p>
               <p>Oh I wolde the Apothecaries of theſe days woulde frame them ſelues to this rule, and the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions lykewiſe on their ſyde, phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycke ſhoulde not then be ſo lyttell regarded and ſet by, as it is now adayes: yea by opprobrious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and tantes deſpiſed of a great many. Nowe I beſeche the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtye and lyuynge God, that ones he woulde make the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and Apothecaries to be of that deſyre and mynde, that eche of theym woulde rather wyſſhe to bee in dede, then to ſeeme or to
<pb facs="tcp:11323:38"/>
be called a ryght, good, and honeſt phyſition, a right good and honeſt Apothecarie.</p>
               <p>And yf they do<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neglecte that goodlye gyfte and grace, I praye God that ones ſome punyſhment maye be appointed by the kynges lawes and ſtatutes for them, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che will enterpriſe to practiſe a ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (ſo healthy to mannes body, when it is well myniſtred, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne ſo hurtefull and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, when it is ignorantlye and raſhely handled) before they know it. Thus muche Syluius. And here I wil make an ende of Apothecaries, now to the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons.<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11323:39"/>
and ſome there bee that can ſcante let a man bloud (which is a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and pretie feate, and yet not ſo harde a thyng to be doone) nor well apply a ventoſe called other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe a cupping glaſſe, vnleſſe they put the man to peyne and trouble. There be ſome that eſteeme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo wel exerciſed and perfect in the arte, that they thynke that no cure can come amiſſe to them: They wyll enterpriſe and take in hande all maner of cures, be they neuer ſo hard or incurable: for they haue feare of nothyng, but raſhely go to worke in all thynges. They wyll cutte, they wyll launce, they wyll canteriſe (whyche they calle ſearyng with a hot burning yron) they wyll ſawe of a legge or an arme of the bodye, they wyll vſe corroſiues that ſhall pearce euen
<pb facs="tcp:11323:39"/>
vnto the hard bones, and they wil make an iſſue almoſte for euery trifle, and for euery diſeaſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſyderynge the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the whole matter, not wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng the ſtrengthe, the age, and the complexion of the bodye, beſydes many other things that are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be conſydered in ſuche caſes. And poſſible it is many times that the paciente hathe nede of ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde medicine, whiche the ſurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can nor may wel geue without the Phyſitions counſayle</p>
               <p>And in dede it were very mete and neceſſarie, that the Surgion ſhould vndertake no hard or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous cure, without the phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s aduyſe. Howbeit as I ſee nowe a dayes, the moſt part of them do al thynges, followynge onely theyr owne fantaſies.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11323:40"/>They ſticke not to geue Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſyropes, and other medicines them ſelues, yea and purgations al ſo: which thinge me ſemeth is very vncomely. It is not reaſon that he that ſhoulde be but as a miniſter vnto the phiſition (as I alleged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of <hi>Galen,</hi> when I intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Poticaries) ſhoulde vſe the parte of a maiſter and philoſopher, and ordeyne ſuche thinges as he knoweth nothing the nature of. It is not vnknowen, that many pore pacientes periſheth vnder ſuche raſhe and lewde ſurgions.</p>
               <p>But to ſaye the trueth, the fault is not ſo muche in them, as in thoſe that geue credite vnto them. For as the world goeth nowe a daies, if a phiſition or ſurgion hath a faixe tonge, &amp; hath alſo ſom what a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodie, and can ſpeake (I wil not
<pb facs="tcp:11323:40"/>
ſaye flatter) indifferently on euery mans ſide, gratifying eche man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his qualitie, deſire and minde: euery man vnles he be very wiſe &amp; circumſpect, wil lightly geue eare and credite vnto him, &amp; acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt him for a diſcret and conning ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Suche a one ſhall lacke nothing, he ſhall be welcome, he ſhall haue much curteſie and pleaſure ſhewed him, finally he ſhal haue his whole hartes deſire, (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is money enough) For ſuch felowes by their ſubtyltie and fayre tongue, will allure more people vnto them, &amp; get themſelues more treaſure in one quarter of a yere, then ſhal an honeſt and good phiſition in the ſpace of thre yeres, and all by their fleringe face &amp; flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering wordes.</p>
               <p>I would to god that al men wold beware of ſuch felowes, &amp; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber
<pb facs="tcp:11323:41"/>
the prouerbe that ſaith: <hi>Dulci ſub melle ſaepe venena <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atent.</hi> Vnder ſwete meats is many times a poy ſon hidde. And as <hi>Virgill</hi> ſaithe: <hi>Hinc procul o pueri fugite, later an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis in herba,</hi> Take hede and flee farre hence O childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the ſnake lieth priuily hid vnder the graſſe.</p>
               <p>It is written in the auncient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of Phiſicke, that in the olde time, the phiſitions were wonte to exerciſe ſurgerie themſelues. Howe beit it hath bene nowe of a longe time, that the Surgions do onely exerciſe this part of phiſicke for ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny conſiderations, and chiefely for this occaſion, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaith <hi>Vita breuis, are vero longa</hi> The life of man is ſhorte in compariſon of the ſcience of Phiſicke whiche is longe. Therfore becauſe the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions can not well geue theym
<pb facs="tcp:11323:41"/>
ſelues to ſtudie diuers other ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: whiche be neceſſary to phiſicke and make medecines, and vſe alſo ſurgerie, and go &amp; viſit their paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes: It hath bene thought good that other men called Surgions (and yet hauing ſufficiente know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege) ſhould haue the office and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie to vſe and applie outward medecines, and not to enterpriſe and vſe all medecines for all diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes both outward and inward, as ſome doeth, for in ſo doyng they go beyond their bondes.</p>
               <p>Surgerie although it be a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuell arte, yet it hath his ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whiche can not be had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out readynge of diuers authors, and ſpecially <hi>Hippocrates, Galen, Aetius, Paulus Aegineta,</hi> and of the latter writers, <hi>Tagaultius, Holle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Bologuinus</hi> and others. As
<pb facs="tcp:11323:42"/>
for <hi>Iohannes de Vigo,</hi> whom the Surgions of our daies doo now moſt follow, I wold not that they ſhould ſo greatly truſt him, becauſe that he is not to be folowed &amp; read without great diſcretion &amp; Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the obſcuritie &amp; doubtes, yea and errours that be in him. He bringeth in manye thinges in his boke, which belongeth rather to the phiſition to knowe &amp; practiſe, then to the Surgion: as Electuaries, potions, purgations &amp; many other inward medicines. If the Surgio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue knowledge in Phiſicke, I meane that he know the compleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the nature of ſimples, and the effect &amp; operation of compoſitions: he may vſe them, els not. For if he do, he ſhal do as the blind man ſho teth at the hare, he ſhal worke at al aduentures, and many times with
<pb facs="tcp:11323:42"/>
the danger of his pacient.</p>
               <p>I much maruell, why the ſurgion ſhould diſdayne to come aſke coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of the Phiſition, when he hath any hard or doubtfull cure, it can be no hindrance to him, and to ſaye the trueth, it is no great profite to the phiſitian, vnles it be for ſome riche man. The good phiſition will vſe the poore as the poore: and the riche partly for his money as well as for his loue and frendſhip. For the phiſition muſt haue his liuyng by ſome kinde of perſons. And not onely the phiſition, but alſo the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticarie and Surgion ſhould deale charitably with the poore, &amp; vſe eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry man accordyng to hys capacity. But this I haue ſpoken, <hi>Velut o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter,</hi> as by the way: Nowe to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Manye perchaunce wyll ſaye<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11323:43"/>
plye any thinge to the ſwellinge, without conſidering whether the body muſt be let bloud or not? whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the ſwellinge or <hi>phlegmon</hi> be yet in <hi>fluxu,</hi> that is a breding: or in ſtatu, that is in the worſt caſe that it can be: or in the declination? whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther or when he ought to vſe reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſiues, reſolutions, or both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? The generall rule of Phiſicke ſaithe, that in the beginning of all inflamations, we ſhould vſe reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſiues, that is medecines to repel and driue backe the fluxion of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours: But I put the caſe that the ſwelling be in the Emunctories, or that one hath the peſtilence: The ſurgion perhappes folowinge the generall rule, will laye a plaſter to repell the ſaid inflamation or ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge. Doth he well thinke you? he doth ſo well that cyther he putteth
<pb facs="tcp:11323:43"/>
the pacient in great ieopardy, or els he killeth him quite.</p>
               <p>Wherfore the ſurgion muſt thinke that a great many things muſt be conſidred mo them one, as often as he vndertaketh any cure of weight And muſte thinke it no ſhame nor reproche, to counſell with a Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſuch matters. For verely I ſaye (to conclude in fewe wordes) that no man, be he ſurgion or poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie, ſhall neuer worke well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a true methode and learninge. For loke what thinge ſo euer he taketh in hande, what cure ſo euer he hath: he beyng deſtitute of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, ſhall neuer bringe it well to paſſe, without the ayde, helpe and counſell of the learned Phiſition: for if he chaunce to do any notable cure, it ſhall be peraduenture more by happe haſard, then by procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:11323:44"/>
and diligence. Here I coulde bring in many other abuſes of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie: as howe ſome pretende and exerciſe phiſicke (to their ſhame, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauynge the people) vnder the cloke of Surgerie: ſome dryue of and linger out the time, to haue the more money. Some be ſo preſump tuous, that wil warrant euery pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient: when oftentymes many by their negligence (and for lacke of a good diet, or ſome other good me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decines whiche ſhoulde be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the phiſition) dye vpon their hands. Some whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue done al that they can, &amp; ſee that their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient begin to go to wrack, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly with all ſpede, they will run to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phiſition w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their pacientes water, and then to aſke counſayle when it is to late: and all becauſe they wylle ſhake of the burdeyne
<pb facs="tcp:11323:44"/>
from theyr owne ſhoulders, to caſt it vpon the Phyſitions necke, and to put all the faulte in hym, if any thyng chance otherwiſe then well: that ſo they may be cleane diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and vnburdened from all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of blame and reproche. Some frome towne to towne, frome market to markette, to vtter their tromperie (theyr ware I woulde haue ſayde) and to ſhew their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng among the homely and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people of the countrey.</p>
               <p>But all theſe wily and deceatful faſhions are not yet throughly kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen, nor can neuer well be, vntyll ſuche tyme as a reformation bee made by ſome law or ſtatute, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I pray God to graunt ſhortely, to his glory, &amp; the Queenes maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties honor, &amp; the profite of we her ſubiectes &amp; common weale.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11323:45"/>
            <head>To bothe the Vniverſities, Oxforde and Cambridge, a Peroration.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THus much I had (right worſhipful) to ſay,</l>
               <l>And to declare moſt playnly to you all:</l>
               <l>The great abuſe committed euery day</l>
               <l>In this our art, whiche phiſike men do call.</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt poyntes I haue in generall</l>
               <l>But onely toucht in this my lytell booke:</l>
               <l>He may know all the matter in ſpeciall,</l>
               <l>Who ſo to it more narrowly wyll looke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I meruayle muche and ſore lament to ſee,</l>
               <l>That ſuch abuſe hath ben ſuffred ſo long:</l>
               <l>And is nowe yet, (it wyll none other be.)</l>
               <l>You and we haue (me thinkes) great wrong:</l>
               <l>Therfore ye ſhould no more the tyme prolong,</l>
               <l>But ſeke ſome meanes the learned to defend,</l>
               <l>With priuileges, that to you doo belong.</l>
               <l>And thus doyng, you ſhall no man offend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I euer had, and haue yet at this houre,</l>
               <l>A great deſpre, bothe in my hart and mynde:</l>
               <l>That euery good phyſition to his power</l>
               <l>Do all thynges well: ſo worſhyp ſhall he fynd.</l>
               <l>But nowe there are phyſitions ſo vnkynde,</l>
               <l>To God and man, that they paſſe not a ſtraw.</l>
               <l>Whiche of bothe endes go before or behynde,</l>
               <l>They are ſo void of truthe and feare of lawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſort wyl now inueye with force &amp; might,</l>
               <l>Straight agaynſt me, and this poore ſely boke,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11323:45"/>(Wherfore I pray, defend me and the right)</l>
               <l>They wyll lay wayt for me, and always looke</l>
               <l>What time the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may deſtroy me with their hoke</l>
               <l>I meane theyr toung ſo venemous and ſharpe:</l>
               <l>But by gods grace &amp; your helpe I ſhall broke</l>
               <l>That wel enough: and not come in their trappe.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>Mollibus haec non eſt, ſed duris dura Securis, Dura ſecat, damnum mollia nulla ferunt.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDINI,</hi> In aedibus Thomae Marſhi.</p>
            <p>1566.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
